Florence Hamilton Collection Relating to Edwin Markham
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Florence Hamilton Collection Relating to Edwin Markham 1857-1959 (bulk 1926-1942)
MSS31393
Hamilton, Florence, 1873-1968
Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940
11,000 items
22 containers plus 15 oversize
12 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Poet and lecturer. Correspondence, poetry, articles and speeches, biographical material, scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, printed matter and other papers pertaining mainly to the poet Edwin Markham.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Hamilton, Florence.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.; Markham, Anna Catherine, 1859-1938--Correspondence.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940--Correspondence.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940. Florence Hamilton collection relating to Edwin Markham. 1869-1956.; Walgreen, Charles R. (Charles Rudolph), 1873-1939.; Walgreen, Myrtle R. Norton, 1879-
Subjects
Literature.; Poetry.
Places
New York (State)--Social life and customs.; United States--Religion.; United States--Social conditions.
Titles
Florence Hamilton papers
Occupations
Lecturers.; Poets.
Provenance
The collection of Florence Hamilton, poet and lecturer, relating to Edwin Markham was given to the Library of Congress by Hamilton from 1937 to 1962. The Rare Book and Special Collections Division transferred some material to the Manuscript Division in 1943 and 1945.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Florence Hamilton Collection Relating to Edwin Markham.
Related Material
Additional material relating to Edwin Markham includes the Edwin Markham Papers in the Manuscript Division and the Edwin Markham Archives in the Horrmann Library, Wagner College, New York, N.Y.
Access and Restrictions
The Florence Hamilton Collection Relating to Edwin Markham is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Edwin Markham
Date Event
1852, Apr. 23 Born Charles Edward Anson Markham, Oregon City, Oregon Territory
1857 1870 Attended school in Suisan and Santa Clara valleys, Calif.
circa1870 Obtained teaching certificate, California College, Vacaville, Calif.
1872 Graduated, San Jose Normal School, San Jose, Calif.
1874 Attended Christian College, Santa Rosa, Calif.
1875 Married Annie Cox (divorced 1884)
1875 1899 Teacher, principal, and school superintendent in Southern California
1880 Published "The Gulf of Night"
1887 Married Caroline E. Bailey (divorced)
1898 Married Anna Catherine Murphy (died 1938)
1899 Published "The Man with the Hoe," San Francisco Examiner Published The Man with the Hoe. New York: Doxey's
circa 1900 Moved to New York, N.Y.
1901 Published Lincoln and Other Poems. New York: McClure, Phillips
1902 Met Florence Hamilton, later his confidential secretary and lecture manager
1910 Charter member, Poetry Society of America
1914 Published with Benjamin B. Lindsey and George Creel Children in Bondage. New York: Hearst's International Library Published California the Wonderful. New York: Hearst's International Library
1915 Published The Shoes of Happiness, and Other Poems. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, Page
1920 Published Gates of Paradise and Other Poems. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, Page
1921 1940 Poet laureate of Oregon
1922 Read "Lincoln, Man of the People" at dedication of Lincoln Memorial, Washington, D.C.
1925 Published Foundation Stones of Success. Chicago: Howard-Severance Co.
1926 Publication of "The Ballad of the Gallows Bird," Century Magazine
1927 Published The Book of Poetry. New York: W. H. Wise
1929 Elected to the Academy of Arts and Letters
1930 Published Songs and Stories. Los Angeles: Powell Publishing Co.
1932 Published New Poems: Eighty Songs at Eighty. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, Doran.
1933 Awarded honorary Literary Doctorate, St. Lawrence University, Canton, N.Y.
1936 Lecture tour in Mexico
1937 Published The Star of Araby. Stapleton, N.Y.: J. Willig Press Awarded $5,000 prize by Academy of American Poets Declared mentally incompetent by a court in New York
1938 Recorded "Edwin Markham Himself," a phonograph album of his principal poems
1940, Mar. 7 Died, Staten Island, N.Y.
Florence Hamilton
Date Event
1873, July 20 Born Florence Danforth, Upper Jay, N.Y.
circa 1890 Married Ernest Hamilton
circa 1920 1936 Confidential secretary and lecture manager for Edwin Markham
1930s 1950s Member and elected official, National League of American Pen Women, Poetry Forum, and Congress of American Poets Lecturer on poetry
1934 Founding member, Academy of American Poets
1936 Dean of women, Summer School of Poetry, National University of Mexico, Mexico City, Mexico
1939 Published A Moment's Monument. New York: Klein-Heimbinder Co.
1942 Published Mirrors and Human Voices. Prairie City, Ill.: James A. Decker Press
1968, Apr. 14 Died, Richmond, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of Florence Hamilton (1873-1968) relating to Edwin Markham spans the years 1857-1959, with the bulk of the material dating from 1926 to 1942. The papers are organized in the following series: Correspondence, Poetry, Speeches and Writings, Unpublished Biography, Scrapbooks, Photographs and Prints, Memorabilia, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize.
The Correspondence consists of letters to and from Edwin Markham, Florence Hamilton, and others. A majority of the letters, however, are written by Markham to Hamilton and concern his lecture tours, stays with Charles R. Walgreen, his health, the poetry of others, and his thanks to Hamilton for her assistance. The correspondence reveals a relationship between the two with some of Markham's letters to Hamilton addressed as "Dear Child" and simply signed as either "A" or "Aprile."
The Poetry series contains poems by Markham and includes his most famous work, "The Man with the Hoe," as well as "Lincoln, the Man of the People," "Ode to Lincoln," "Ballad of the Gallows Bird," and "Our Israfel." His notebooks of poems span the length of his career. Of interest also is the guestbook in which Markham wrote poems when staying at Hamilton's home in Wellesley Hills, Massachusetts, a place he referred to as "The House with the Smiling Face."
The Speeches and Writings file includes articles, speeches, a radio script, and a motion picture script. Many of Markham's works cover social and religious issues as well as poetry. Markham also wrote about individuals including the American realist author and literary critic William Dean Howells.
The Unpublished Biography series consists largely of Hamilton's typescript of " The Man with the Hoe, the Poem, the Poet, and the Problem: The Intellectual Biography of Edwin Markham" that was to have been published in 1936. Included also are biographical sketches of Markham, letters authorizing Hamilton to write his biography, drafts of the work, and a photograph of Markham and Hamilton.
The Scrapbooks series includes clippings, photographs, programs, correspondence, and poems covering the personal lives and writings of Markham and Hamilton. Volumes 3 and 10 pertain mostly to Hamilton and document her poetry, her relationship to Markham, and her life as a poet in New York. Volume 8 contains a copy of Markham's will, while Volume 7 is filled with his obituary notices from 1940. Many of Markham's poems in the scrapbooks have been inscribed to Hamilton.
Other photographs are located in the Photographs and Prints series as well as a print of the painting "The Man with the Hoe" by the French artist Jean-François Millet. The Memorabilia series includes a plaster cast of Markham's hand, a strand of his hair, and horoscopes written for him.
The Miscellany is largely comprised of books inscribed by Markham to Hamilton or annotated by him. Eleven volumes were authored by Markham's friend, Thomas Lake Harris, and others were written or edited by Markham. Of interest among Markham's personal documents is a copyright certificate from the Library of Congress dated 1900 for the poem "Lincoln, the Great Commoner." The printed matter consists of annotated articles, clippings, programs, and prose and poems about and by Markham, many of which seemed to have been collected by Hamilton for her biography of him.
The Addition includes programs, poems, and articles pertaining to Hamilton; some correspondence of Markham's wife, Anna Catherine Markham; and a book of poems by Markham's mother, Elizabeth Markham, published in 1921.
The Oversize is comprised of poems, scrapbooks, photographs, and memorabilia.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in ten series:
Correspondence, 1900-1950
Poetry, 1881-1936
Speeches and Writings, 1917-1932
Unpublished Biography, 1922-1959
Scrapbooks, 1872-1955
Photographs and Prints, 1869-1935
Memorabilia, 1880-1936
Miscellany, circa 1876-1950
Addition, 1857-1958
Oversize, 1869-1953
Container List
- Correspondence, 1900-1950 (Box 1-2)
  Letters to and from Markham, Hamilton, and others, with most from Markham to Hamilton.
  Hamilton's letters from Markham are organized separately from her general correspondence; both files are arranged chronologically. Markham's correspondnece with others is organized according to letters received and sent and therein chronologically.
  - Hamilton, Florence (Box 1)
    - General, 1931-1940, 1950, undated (Box 1)
    - Markham, Edwin (Box 1)
      - 1923-1932, (7 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1933 (Box 1)
        - Jan.-Oct. (Box 1)
        - Nov.-Dec. (Box 2)
      - 1934-1936, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Markham, Edwin (Box 2)
    - Received, 1911-1912, 1919, 1931-1936, undated (Box 2)
    - Sent, 1900, 1919, 1925-1938, undated (Box 2)
- Poetry, 1881-1936 (Box 3-5)
  Handwritten, typescript, and printed copies of poems by Markham with some in notebooks and some in sheet music.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or type of material. The notebooks are arranged chronologically.
  - Guestbook of poems by Markham composed at Hamilton's house, 1924-1932 (Box 3)
  - Notebooks (Box 3)
    - No. 1, circa 1881 (Box 3)
    - No. 2, 1883 (Box 3)
    - No. 3, circa 1918 (Box 3)
    - No. 4, 1927 (Box 3)
    - No. 5, 1929-1934 (Box 3)
    - No. 6, 1931-1934 (Box 3)
    - No. 7, 1933 (Box 3)
    - No. 8, 1935 (Box 3)
    - No. 9, 1935 (Box 3)
    - No. 10, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Enclosures, 1882-1883, undated (Box 3)
  - Sheet music, 1899, 1906-1916, 1932-1936, undated (Box 4)
  - Titled poems (Box 4)
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1931-1936, undated (Box 4)
    - "Ballad of the Gallows Bird," 1935 (Box 4)
    - "B-F" miscellaneous, 1929-1936, undated (Box 4)
    - "G-H" miscellaneous, 1929-1936, undated (Box 4)
    - "I-K" miscellaneous, 1931-1936, undated (Box 4)
    - "Lincoln, the Man of the People," 1936 See Oversize (Box 5)
    - "L" miscellaneous, 1924, 1931-1935, undated (Box 5)
    - "The Man with the Hoe," 1933, undated See also Oversize (Box 5)
    - "M-N" miscellaneous, 1921, 1931-1936, undated (Box 5)
    - "Ode to Lincoln," 1936 See also Oversize (Box 5)
    - "Our Israfel," 1925 See Oversize (Box 5)
    - "O-S" miscellaneous, 1929-1936, undated (Box 5)
    - "The Twin Flags," 1936 See Oversize (Box 5)
    - "T-Z" miscellaneous, 1899, 1929-1936, undated (Box 5)
  - Untitled and fragments, undated (Box 5)
- Speeches and Writings, 1917-1932 (Box 6)
  Handwritten and typescript copies of speeches, articles, a radio script, and a motion picture script.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "A-F" miscellaneous, 1917, undated (Box 6)
  - "G-L" miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Man with the Hoe and the Storm It Started," undated (Box 6)
  - "M-P" miscellaneous, 1923-1930, undated (Box 6)
  - "S-T" miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
  - "William Dean Howells," undated (Box 6)
  - "W" miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
  - Unidentified, fragments, and notes, 1920, 1932, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Unpublished Biography, 1922-1959 (Box 7)
  A typescript, drafts, authorization letters, biographical sketches, and a photograph relating to Hamilton's unpublished biography of Markham, "The Man with the Hoe, the Poem, the Poet, and the Problem: The Intellectual Biography of Edwin Markham."
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Authorization letters, biographical sketches, and a photograph, 1922-1934, undated (Box 7)
  - Drafts, undated (Box 7)
  - Typescript, 1930-1934, 1959, (9 folders) (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks, 1872-1955 (Box 7)
  Scrapbooks of clippings, photographs, correspondence, programs, poems, and photocopies pertaining to Markham and Hamilton.
  Arranged by volume number assigned by Hamilton or by title.
  - Vols. 1-2, 1872, 1899-1946, undated See Oversize, (2 vols.) (Box 7)
  - Vols. 3-4, 1919-1952, undated See Oversize, (2 vols.) (Box 7)
  - Vol. 5, 1932-1952, undated See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Vol. 6, 1899-1941, 1948-1955, undated See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Vols. 7, 9-10, 1933-1953, undated See Oversize, (3 vols.) (Box 7)
  - Vol. 8, 1882, 1923-1942, 1952-1953, undated See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Oregon friends, 1921 See Oversize (Box 7)
- Photographs and Prints, 1869-1935 (Box 7)
  Photographs of Markham and Hamilton and others and a print of the original painting "The Man with the Hoe."
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Photographs, 1869, 1880, 1903-1907, 1918-1935, undated See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Print, "The Man with the Hoe," undated See Oversize (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1880-1936 (Box 7)
  A plaster cast of Markham's hand, a strand of his hair, and horoscopes.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or title.
  - Astrological Review, 1936 See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Hair strand of Markham, 1880 See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Horoscopes for Markham, circa 1935 See Oversize (Box 7)
  - Plaster cast of Markham's hand, undated See Oversize (Box 7)
- Miscellany, circa 1876-1950 (Box 8-17)
  Inscribed books, mostly by Markham to Hamilton, and personal documents and printed matter.
  - Books (Box 8)
    - By Thomas Lake Harris, circa 1876, 1878, 1886-1892 (Box 8)
    - Inscribed to Hamilton, 1887-1910, 1916-1933, 1943 (Box 9-12)
    - Written or edited by Markham, 1899, 1909-1938 (Box 13-15)
  - Personal documents of Markham, 1879-1883, 1900-1924 (Box 16)
  - Printed matter (Box 16)
    - Annotated articles and clippings, 1898, 1911, 1924-1938, 1947-1950, undated (Box 16)
    - Programs, 1881, 1917, 1926-1942, undated (Box 16)
    - Prose and poems (Box 16)
      - About Markham (Box 16)
        - 1899-1902, 1916-1940, (2 folders) (Box 16)
        - Undated (Box 17)
      - By Markham 1880, 1899-1943, undated, (6 folders) (Box 17)
- Addition, 1857-1958 (Box 18-22)
  Correspondence, poems, articles, printed matter, scripts, and phototographs.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and thereunder by name of person.
  - Correspondence (Box 18)
    - Hamilton, Florence, 1926-1956, undated, (5 folders) (Box 18)
    - Markham, Anna Catherine, 1909, 1919-1923, 1932-1935, undated (Box 19)
    - Markham, Edwin 1899-1936, undated, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - Miscellany, 1918, 1926, 1933-1941, undated (Box 19)
  - Literary file (Box 20)
    - Hamilton, Florence, drafts, notes, and poems, 1940, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Markham, Edwin (Box 20)
      - Articles and drafts, 1918, 1930, undated (Box 20)
      - Newsreel documentary, "The Romantic Days of '49," circa 1914 (Box 20)
      - Poems, 1900-1935, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Miscellany (Box 21)
    - Articles and poems about Markham, 1932-1941, undated, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Books annotated and dedicated by Markham (Box 21)
      - 1857, 1884, 1903, (3 folders) (Box 21)
      - 1916 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, notes, photographs, and poems, 1930-1942, undated (Box 22)
    - Radio broadcasts and a speech, 1921, 1932, undated (Box 22)
  - Printed matter (Box 22)
    - Hamilton, Florence, 1930-1950, 1958, undated (Box 22)
    - Markham, Edwin, 1899-1903, 1916-1917, 1926, 1932-1942, 1948, 1954-1955, undated (Box 22)
    - Miscellany, 1921, 1926, 1930-1948, undated (Box 22)
- Oversize, 1869-1953 (Box OV 1-OV 15)
  Poems, scrapbooks, photographs, and memorabilia.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Poetry (Box OV 1)
    - Titled poems (Box OV 1)
      - "Lincoln, the Man of the People," 1936, (Container 5) (Box OV 1)
      - "The Man with the Hoe," 1933, undated, (Container 5) (Box OV 2)
      - "Ode to Lincoln," 1936, (Container 5) (Box OV 3)
      - "Our Israfel," 1925, (Container 5) (Box OV 4)
      - "The Twin Flags," 1936, (Container 5) (Box OV 5)
  - Scrapbooks, (Container 7) (Box OV 6)
    - Vols. 1-2, 1872, 1899-1946, undated (Box OV 6)
    - Vols. 3-4, 1919-1952, undated (Box OV 7)
    - Vol. 5, 1932-1952, undated (Box OV 8)
    - Vol. 6, 1899-1941, 1948-1955, undated (Box OV 9)
    - Vols. 7, 9-10, 1933-1953, undated (Box OV 10)
    - Vol. 8, 1882, 1923-1942, 1952-1953, undated (Box OV 11)
    - Oregon friends, 1921 (Box OV 12)
  - Photographs and Prints, (Container 7) (Box OV 13)
    - Photographs, 1869, 1880, 1903-1907, 1918-1935, undated (Box OV 13)
    - Print, "The Man with the Hoe," undated (Box OV 14)
  - Memorabilia, (Container 7) (Box OV 15)
    - Astrological Review, 1936 (Box OV 15)
    - Hair strand of Markham, 1880 (Box OV 15)
    - Horoscopes for Markham, circa 1935 (Box OV 15)
    - Plaster cast of Markham's hand, undated (Box OV 15)